<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short account, or state of Mr. Sheridan's case before the late House of Commons in a letter to J.T.</title>
            <author>L. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T25A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203698</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825277</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825277</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29655</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63465)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29655)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2022:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short account, or state of Mr. Sheridan's case before the late House of Commons in a letter to J.T.</title>
                  <author>L. T.</author>
                  <author>J. T.</author>
                  <author>Sheridan, Thomas, 1646-ca. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Hindmarsh at the Bull in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: L.T.</note>
                  <note>"The speech of Mr. Tho. Sheridan, after his examination before the late House of Commons, on Wednesday the 15th. of December, 1680", B1v-C3r.</note>
                  <note>Imprint has "Cornhill". Variant: imprint has "Cornnill".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sheridan, Thomas, 1646-ca. 1688.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29655:1"/>
            <p>A Short ACCOUNT, Or STATE of Mr. Sheridans CASE Before the Late <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> In a LETTER to <hi>J. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Hindmarſh</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29655:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29655:2"/>
            <head>A ſhort Account or State of Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi>'s Caſe before the late <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> in a Letter to <hi>J. T.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>OME Years ſince, I ſent you a long Letter under the Title of <hi>J. L.</hi> relating to an affair, wherein Mr. <hi>S.</hi> was deeply concerned; this gave you ſo much ſatisfaction, that I have thence ſufficient encouragement to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture another; eſpecially conſidering his vindication is much more neceſſary in the preſent inſtance, and that you are ſtill his Friend, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom of all Men living he is perhaps the beſt known. Under that Character you were mention'd in the Copy of a Letter carri'd among other of his Papers to the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> writ in his favour to a great Miniſter by the late E. of <hi>Or.</hi> for whom living, and for whoſe memory, both your Gr. and he had, and ever muſt have, a juſt value and veneration.</p>
            <p>You will find you may ſtill own this Gentleman without bluſhing, and to ſhew you were not deceiv'd in the opinion of his Integrity, I have taken the pains, for your ſake, as well as for his, whoſe Friend I own my ſelf, to gather up, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey to you, the Hiſtory and occaſion, that has made him as publickly known in this, as he was before in another Kingdom. I promiſe you an impartial Relation, and by it you will ſee, that Envy and Malice, where with he has been long aſſaulted, have to little purpoſe ſpit their Venom.</p>
            <p>You are not to learn the cauſe of his coming for <hi>England</hi> in <hi>June,</hi> 1677. nor knowing his temper, to wonder that havi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29655:3"/>receiv'd ſome favours from his <hi>R. H.</hi> gratitude oblig'd him to an acknowledgment, and honour and generoſity to make and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow it in the time of that great Prince's adverſity, whom he found by the unſteddy courſe of Humane affairs, and the craft and malice of deſigning Men, fallen from being the Peoples greateſt Favourite into their higheſt Diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>Soon after, when the D. in obedience to his Royal Brother's commands went into a temporary Exile, which however o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe uneaſie, was chearfully undergone by him, who al-always reſign'd his own, to the will of his Prince: Your Friend having little to hinder, laid hold of that opportunity, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> and there ſpending moſt of the time he was abroad, expreſs'd his Obligations and Duty in the beſt manner he was able.</p>
            <p>This, and his openly owning himſelf devoted to his <hi>R.</hi> H's intereſt, while conſiſtent with Loyalty, gave occaſion to his Adverſaries, whom envy had encreas'd, to vent their Spleen, and endeavour to ſully his Reputation, of all things to him moſt dear, by many falſe Inſinuations, and indeed Diabolical Inventions, hoping thereby to diſable him from rivalling them in any future pretenſion. He is not ignorant of the Authors, nor the train, who the better to compaſs their <hi>honeſt</hi> Deſign, hatch'd by one, that Mole-like, works under ground, and he thinks in the dark, they reſolv'd at once his ruine, by rendring him odious to the Publick, to the Country, to the King, and to the Court; and therefore he was no ſooner brought before the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> than he was repreſented to his Soveraign, as one that had ſpoken ill of His Majeſty, and to the wonder of himſelf and others, this was firſt whiſper'd to, and after ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted by, a great Lord, to whom Mr. <hi>S.</hi> owns himſelf oblig'd for ſeveral favours. and in particular for a very kind recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory Letter ſome Years ſince to Mr. Secretary <hi>Coven</hi>— But that which makes his ſurprize the greater, is, his not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to find, on his part, any cauſe for the change of this Noble-man's greatly valu'd good opinion, of which he hop'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mſelf ſtill poſſeſt, becauſe certain he never diſoblig'd his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29655:3"/>Lordſhip, and defies any Man to make out that in word or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, he ever ſpake or did irreverently or diſloyally of the King, whoſe Service, you know, no man has more zealouſly promoted, nor leſs ineffectually, according to his Station and Power. However, in the height of his-misfortune, when to all he did not appear guiltleſs, he had the happineſs to have a Gentleman of Honour and Quality (who by the recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our deceas'd, and never to be forgotten noble Friend, ſeveral Years ago, took him into his particular favour and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance) publickly to aſſert his Integrity, his Service, and his Loyalty. An Act of Friendſhip, he is bound by all the ties of Gratitude, ever to remember and acknowledge; few Men in this Age having the courage, or the honeſty, to own any Man in adverſity, or to defend innocence, when endeavour'd to be run down by faction, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe, and tumult. The ground of this Diſcourſe in publick at the King's Dinner, was the Copy of a Letter found among Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s Papers, which plainly appears to have come from another, but not to him, to whom had it been directed, he could not be therefore criminal, it being in no Man's Power to prevent any Poſt-Letter. And yet give me leave to ſay, that ingenuity and good nature may eaſily and very naturally make a candid interpretation of this Paper; wherein what ever Injury was contain'd, they are moſtly, if not only, guilty, who ſince the ſeizing Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s Writings, have ſent Copies of it to all the <hi>Coffe-houſes</hi> of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to give you the Story from the beginning, you are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the firſt week the Parliament met, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> was told by a Perſon of Honour, that he was deſign'd to be brought into Trouble: This was overheard from ſeveral, among whom were ſome Members then looking on at Mrs. <hi>C.</hi> ſtanding in the Pillory, whereupon he was advis'd to withdraw: Receiving the ſame account from many others, and yet confident in his Innocence, he reſolv'd not to ſtir. Every day he was alarm'd afreſh, and told of great enquiries made after his Actions, and himſelf cenſur'd for a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> a <hi>Coleman,</hi> and a <hi>Jeſuit.</hi> At length one <hi>Peter Norris</hi> makes complaint of his being Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29655:4"/>at <hi>Daver</hi> by Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkin</hi>'s order. Mr. Secretary ſaid, as I am inform'd, what he did was not unknown to the King and Council. Upon this occaſion Mr. <hi>S.</hi> was nam'd and a Committee appointed to examin the matter. Mr. <hi>S.</hi> appears, and acknowledges, he had given a deſcription of <hi>Peter Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> to Mr. Secretary about the latter end of <hi>May</hi> laſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him that he was told, this Man knew as much of the bottom of the <hi>Plot,</hi> as any in <hi>England,</hi> and was gone into <hi>France</hi> to fetch over a Prieſt ſuppos'd equally knowing.</p>
            <p>'Tis not neceſſary to entertain you withal the queſtions, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forreign to this matter, by ſome of the Committee put to Mr. <hi>S.</hi> 'tis enough to tell you that he truly, though perhaps not ſatisfactorily, anſwer'd all, attended their pleaſures a whole week, was thrice before them, once with Dr. <hi>D.</hi> from whom as News he publickly had the ſtory, and after, the Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Dr. himſelf openly confeſs'd. I know not whether it be neceſſary to acquaint you, that whatever account the Dr. had, Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s was not exact as to <hi>Norris</hi>'s bringing the Prieſt into <hi>England;</hi> for it appear'd at the Committee by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers taken with <hi>Norris</hi> at landing, that he was to Conduct him to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> to Sr. <hi>W. W.</hi> then there, and that he had pretended to be ſent by Dr. <hi>T.</hi> in conjunction with the E. of <hi>Sh.</hi> and another Noble Peer, that the Prieſt had been dead a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 8 Months, before he began his Journey; a Journey un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken upon as good an account and ſure information, as that of a Juſtice of Peace of <hi>Weſtminſler,</hi> who rid Poſt 100 Miles to bring alive from the Country <hi>Beddingfield</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> Buried 12 Months before out of the Gate-houſe. It happen'd the evening of that Day Mr. <hi>S.</hi> was Commanded to attend the Committee, I was in Company with ſeveral Perſons, of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, when news was ſent that the E. of <hi>P.</hi> was carri'd to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and Mr. <hi>S.</hi> to the <hi>Gate-houſe,</hi> who in half an hour after came in himſelf, and gueſs'd the Perſon, and concluded what the other cou'd not deny, that the ſtory was from one that wiſh'd it had been true, not out of Malice to Mr. <hi>S.</hi> beyond his name a Stranger, but to a very great Perſon. After Mr. <hi>S</hi>'s
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29655:4"/>firſt Examination, he receiv'd by the Penny-poſt two Letters in unknown hands, without any name, the one directed to his Lodging, the other to the Royal <hi>Coffee-houſe;</hi> the one in Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to three Perſons of Honour, his acquaintance, nam'd in the Letter, adviſing him to fly, if he did not reſolve to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as to him at leaſt impoſſibilities againſt the D. the other was more Terrible, tho' both mix'd with threats and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and in this place for receiving his anſwer, and after for meeting appointed. But theſe he look'd upon as bugbears, fit only to work upon Children and Cowards.</p>
            <p>Having produc'd the Dr. who was his Author, he look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf acquitted from any further trouble, yet ſome angry Perſons, diſpleas'd a hole was not found in his Coat, offer'd wagers he wou'd be lay'd by the Heels in ten days, of which, by two very great Perſons, notice was given him, with advice to retire, at the Tria! of my Lord <hi>Stafford;</hi> but reſolv'd to encounter the worſt cou'd happen, he utterly rejected the Motion.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Thurſday, December</hi> 9. He ſound it was no longer a jeſt, for it was then order'd that Mr. <hi>S.</hi>'s and <hi>D. D</hi>'s Papers ſhou'd be ſeiz'd, and themſelves brought in Cuſtody of the Serjeant at Arms to the Bar of the houſe. In purſuance of this, ſome Members were ſent to their Lodgings between 12 and 1, who coming to Mr. S. 's were told he was abroad; they meeting one of his Servants, ſent for him, who finding his Maſter at the <hi>Coffee-houſe,</hi> acquainted him that Four of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons whom he knew not, ſtay'd for him; he goes to 'um im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately. They after a diligent ſearch for his Papers, ſpoke of his being ſent for by a Meſſenger. He anſwer'd, that was unneceſſary to one that was ready to wait on them to their houſe, whither as he was going, they met their Officer, and took him into the Coach. Mr. <hi>S.</hi> not long after being call'd to the Bar; was ask'd wheter a Paper then ſhew'd him was his Writing: He anſwer'd it was not, then two lines at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of <hi>Norris</hi>'s deſcription were ſhewn, which he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd. After ſome other queſtions he was Commanded to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29655:5"/>withdraw, and a Committee order'd to ſee the Serjeant ſearch his pockets. But to prevent that trouble, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> had deliver'd them all his Papers, ſo that nothing cou'd be found ſave a purſe of Gold, out of which in order to be ſearch'd for Papers, more Guinnies were ſaid to be tumbl'd, than it cou'd poſſibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. But excepting your Friends fortune, every Molehill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to him was reputed a Mountain, and no doubt many were big with expectations what he ſhould bring forth, who was ſaid to have ſeveral <hi>Colemans</hi> in his belly; and therefore perhaps it was, that the Serjeant ſent him to Lodge at a Mid-wifes, where being laid, in ſpight of all art and labour, the long hop'd for conceiv'd great iſſue, upon delivery, was found dwindl'd to a Mouſe. <hi>Parturiunt montes</hi> — He was 4 or 5 times at the Bar that day, and as often the next; his ſtory being matter of fact, was found to agree exactly with the Doctor's, who was not ſeldomer examin'd, and tho no crime was object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor any information made, yet was he confin'd a cloſe Priſoner, and the Meſſenger told, if he ſuffer'd his eſcape, his own Life wou'd be in danger: an opinion, that cannot be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently admir'd by thoſe who conſider, that, had he any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of guilt, he might with eaſe have avoided that days fury.</p>
            <p>The worthy Coll. <hi>M.</hi> whom you knew in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Title of Capt. came in to accuſe Mr. <hi>S.</hi> but of a Circumſtance, that if true, cou'd not amount to a Crime. Yet this ſeem'd ſo great, that the Gent. cou'd hardly bring it out in Mr. <hi>S.</hi>'s. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, whatever he had done before, uttering then his words ſo like a Mouſe in a Cheeſe, that the <hi>Speaker</hi> was forc'd twice to command the raiſing his Voice.</p>
            <p>After Mr. <hi>S.</hi> was committed, great and narrow Enquiries and Endeavours were made to find or make him more obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but in vain: His Innocence was his ſecurity from peril, tho' not from charge and trouble. Among others, Doctor <hi>Tongue</hi>'s Son in <hi>Newgate</hi> was examin'd, whom Mr. <hi>S.</hi> never ſaw, having induſtriouſly avoided all that were or ſtood rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Kings Evidence. The Servant-maid of his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29655:5"/>was ſent for, not only to the Bar, but to <hi>Coffee-houſes</hi> and <hi>Taverns,</hi> promis'd and encourag'd, threatn'd and advis'd; but alas, ſhe cou'd not anſwer expectations. Even a little young Girl of about Eleven years old, not above Ten days his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, was very ſtrictly Catechiz'd, concerning his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and Converſation about the Parliament. Sure, theſe perſons beleiv'd him Maſter of none, or of much leſs under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, than they have ſince reported him.</p>
            <p>But on <hi>Saturday</hi> following Dr. <hi>D.</hi> who confeſs'd himſelf a <hi>R. C.</hi> was without Fees (tho' he was ſore'd to pay them) or Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, diſcharg'd. Mr. <hi>S.</hi> hearing of this, writes a long Letter to an honourable Member of the Committee, praying his Lordſhip to repreſent to the Houſe what he thought moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial. On <hi>Monday</hi> his Lordſhip by an Order of the Houſe was allow'd to ſee Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and bring him a Letter open'd by the <hi>Speaker,</hi> relating to a particular concern of another, from whence mighty Diſcoveries were expected, but they came to nothing. By this Member he pray'd to have liberty to ſpeak for himſelf the next day, but hearing nothing from him, he wrote to the <hi>Speaker</hi> on <hi>Tueſday,</hi> entreating he might appear before them, and not ſuffer under <hi>Arbitrary power</hi> ſo much dreaded from others. Hereupon Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi> was pleas'd on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the <hi>15th,</hi> to have him ſent for; being call'd in, he was told, if he had any Diſcovery to make, the Houſe was ready to receive it. To this he reply'd, That as to the <hi>Plot,</hi> he cou'd have none, but he had another relating to himſelf; <hi>viz.</hi> To know what was his Crime, and who his Accuſers, and that he might according to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> anſwer for himſelf. To this was ſaid, They knew his Parts were not much ſhort of the Perſon's he ſucceeded, and that he muſt not think to impoſe upon ſo great and wiſe an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> by ſtudi'd <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Speeches.</hi> Mr. <hi>S.</hi> reply'd, If he cou'd, he wou'd not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by any Rhetorical flouriſhes to deceive them with <hi>Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods;</hi> That he deſign'd nothing but Truth very plainly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; That he hop'd their <hi>Juſtice</hi> would give him leave to <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate himſelf,</hi> and ſhew the <hi>unreaſonableneſs</hi> of running down
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29655:6"/>a Man upon general <hi>Sarmiſes</hi> and malicious <hi>Reports,</hi> or of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding him guilty, before he was Heard or Convicted. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was order'd to withdraw, and after ſome ſhort De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate call'd in, and allow'd the Favour he deſir'd; but with Caution, not to be tedious. Being thus permitted, he began the following <hi>Speech,</hi> out of which he omitted very little, and is the ſame in Subſtance with what he writ in ſeveral <hi>Letters</hi> to <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Committee</hi> appointed for his Examination; <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord <hi>Auneſley,</hi> Sir <hi>R. Clayton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Rovel. Gwin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <head>The Speech of Mr. <hi>Tho. Sheridan,</hi> after his Examination before the late <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> On <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the <hi>15th.</hi> of <hi>December, 1680.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>TIs, I confeſs Sir, a great Misfortune to fall under the Diſpleaſure of the Honourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, it is a Burden, no Man, tho' never ſo great, is able to bear; It cannot then be a wonder, if ſo inconſiderable a Perſon, and of ſo little ſtrength as I, ſhou'd ſtoop under the weight; Not that I fear any Danger to my Perſon, but grieve for the wounds it gives my Reputation, which I have always valu'd above my life, and that it might be preſerv'd ſpotleſs, I have ever made it my ſtudy to <hi>keep a good Conſcience, void of Offence, towards God, and towards Man;</hi> And Therefore I little expected to be brought as a Criminal to This Bar, or any Tribunal.</p>
                        <p>But I am convinc'd, Innocence is no ſecurity againſt the Darts of Envy or Malice, and that he who will hazard his Body or his Soul, may take away the Life and Fame of any one at pleaſure; 'tis to men of ſuch principles I owe my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Trouble: I do not ſay this to reflect upon any Member of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29655:6"/>this Great and Honourable Aſſembly. My Evil is from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Doors, and I know the Authors, and the Contrivance, ſo well, that, if it were convenient, I cou'd name them, and trace the whole Chain, Link by Link, to the firſt, hammer'd by Prejudice, and particular Intereſt.</p>
                        <p>I do not wonder that, in the preſent Circumſtances, you ſhou'd have one Ear open to all reports that any way relate to the publick, this is due to your Station, and to your Prudence; And becauſe Juſtice and your Honour require it, I as little doubt your reſerving the other Ear for the Pleas and Defence, of the Accus'd, or that you will Condemn any Man unheard. Upon this aſſurance it is, that I am bold to beg, with all due reſpect and reverence, that I may have liberty to ſpeak for my ſelf without interruption. If you are pleas'd to grant me this favour, I will uſe it as fully and briefly as I can, for your ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and my own vindication.</p>
                        <p>I have been repreſented (I hope without offence I may ſay, traduc'd, for ſo I can make it appear) for a perſon of no For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, a <hi>Papist,</hi> a ſecond <hi>Coleman,</hi> and what is more rediculous, tho' not more falſe, a Jeſuit and the Duke's Confeſſor.</p>
                        <p>In clearing my ſelf from theſe Aſperſions, I muſt be ſorc'd, to ſay ſomething, which nothing but neceſſity, that either has none, or breaks all Laws, can excuſe from vanity. As that I was born a Gentleman, of one of the Antienteſt Families, and related to many Conſiderable, in <hi>Ireland;</hi> in one County there is a Caſtle, and a large Demean, and in another a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tract of Land for ſeveral Miles together, yet known by our Name. I need not ſay who was the head or chief, 'tis too much that my Grandfather was the laſt that enjoy'd the Eſtate, and that my Father, left an Orphan in the beginning of King <hi>Jame</hi>'s Reign, ſoon found himſelf diſpoſſeſs'd, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the World, that whole County, with five others in <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> being intirely eſcheated to the Crown. My Parents <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> my Mother a Gentlewoman of <hi>England</hi> of good Fortune, a <hi>Foſter,</hi> who for my Fathers ſake, quitted her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and her Relations, both fam'd for honeſty, for their Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29655:7"/>and Sufferings in the <hi>late Rebellion,</hi> when my Father ſcap'd twice narrowly with his Life, and at laſt was forc'd to fly, for relieving and protecting both the Fortunes and Perſons of very many <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To my Birth I had a ſuitable Education; I have ſome ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence to Letters, am not altogether a Stranger to the Civil-law, nor the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> the means intended for my Livelihood.</p>
                        <p>But, without my ſeeking or knowledge, ſome Friends pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd for me the Collectorſhip of the Cuſtoms of <hi>Cork,</hi> and the management of moſt of the Inland Revenue of that County: This Imployment, and the Accidents attending it, together with that of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Prizes, and others in the laſt War with <hi>Holland,</hi> put into <hi>Kinſale,</hi> enabl'd me to bring for my own proportion of Advance-money, for the preſent Revenue-Farm of <hi>Ireland,</hi> 9532 <hi>l.</hi> as appears upon Record in the <hi>Chancery</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and being by a Brother of mine, then here, without my privity or deſire, engag'd in this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and a ſtranger to all the Partnerſhip, excepting one, <hi>June</hi> laſt was three years I ſold my Intereſt for 4000 <hi>l.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit This Money I imploy'd in Corporation and Church-Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in Mortgages, and other Securities, at 10 <hi>l. per cent.</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of that Kingdom. And after this account, if I have no viſible real Eſtate, I hope no man can doubt but that I may live independently, tho' beſides, I happen to be a younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo far from bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> prejudice, that it's poſſible to prove my advantage, being deſign'd the Heir of two elder Brothers, who neither have, nor are like to have any Children. The Bills of Exchange, drawn, and remitted to and from <hi>Ireland,</hi> by Sir <hi>John Frederick</hi> and Company, Mr. <hi>D. Arthur,</hi> and other known Merchants, will ſhew my proper Fond, and no Man's Bounty, ſupported my Expences; and therefore, becauſe I can with great Truth, I do the more freely declare, That I neither have, nor ever had any Relation to the Duke or Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> as a Servant or Dependant, a Sallary-man or Penſioner, and was ſo far from ſucceeding Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> that his Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29655:7"/>never enter'd into my Thoughts, taken up with Affairs of a far different nature. My Journey to <hi>Flanders</hi> was no way criminal, and in a great meaſure the effect of curioſity, having before ſeen very little of that Countrey, <hi>Holland,</hi> or <hi>Germany;</hi> and as I went not with the Duke, ſo my return in his Train was purely accident.</p>
                        <p>For my Religion, as I was born of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Parents, ſo I was all along bred a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and (by the Grace of God) will live and die in this Profeſſion; for it is not ſo much owing to the chance of Education, as to my choice, being ſatisfi'd by Reaſon, by Scripture, and the Laws of my Country, no inconſiderable Argument, that of all, it is the moſt purely Chriſtian.</p>
                        <p>Since I was ſeventeen years of Age I have gone duly to Church, and ſeveral times in every Year receiv'd the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I did ſo twice while in <hi>Fianders,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Lake</hi> and Dr. <hi>Doughty</hi> (the Duke's Chaplains) and others can witneſs; and I have done ſo ſix times ſince my return thence; there are in this Honourable Houſe that can teſtify ſome part of this Truth. I have taken the Oathes of Allegiance and Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy eleven times, am ready to ſubmit to all further injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Law in matters of Religion, have in Diſputes encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, tho unwillingly, with many of the ſeveral Orders abroad, remain'd unſhaken in my Principles; This at <hi>Ghent,</hi> putting a Jeſuit (more zealous than the reſt) into great Paſſion, made him pronounce me obſtinate, and declare, <hi>He cou'd ſooner bring over ten of the moſt rigid Phanaticks of</hi> England, <hi>than hope to make me a Proſelyte.</hi> Now if all this be not ſufficient to wipe off the imputation of Popery, I conſeſs I am to ſeek for a cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
                        <p>Among other 'tis objected, That by my Intereſt in his <hi>R. H.</hi> I got my Brother made a Biſhop, in oppoſition to the Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and contrary to Merit. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That my Brother has been as much, and as injuriouſly, though not ſo publickly, defam'd as I; that he came off with Honour; that a peek between two great Lords of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29655:8"/>and one of the greateſt of this, did not only prevent his being ſooner promoted, but was the occaſion of his being beſpatter'd with many falſhoods and calumnies; that few in <hi>Ireland</hi> deſerve it better; that what he enjoys, he obtain'd not in oppoſition to, though without the recommendation of, the chief Governour, nor by the mediation of the Duke, but of a great Miniſter, in the preſence of my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> from the King's immediate Grace openly ſhewn in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and with a particular mark of His Royal Favour.</p>
                        <p>I hope 'tis no Crime to honour and revere the Duke as he is a Prince, or if a private Man to love and value his innate Worth and Qualities; or to have ſaid, as it is reported, (I wiſh nothing elſe had been with leſs Truth) That I wou'd ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard my Life and Fortune to do him any lawful and juſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: If it be a Crime, as I can no ways apprehend of the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of my King, while publickly pray'd for in all the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the three Kingdoms, I confeſs my ſelf guilty; But I am not ſo wedded to his Intereſts, as to eſpouſe or purſue them, if he can have any ſuch, contrary to the Duty I owe, and ever will pay, my Soveraign, my Country, my Religion, and my God.</p>
                        <p>And I do here moſt ſolemnly proteſt, as I hope for Heaven, if I knew him in any inſtance a Conſpirator or a Traytor, I wou'd not only deteſt, but endeavour to bring him to publick Juſtice; and if ever he can be prov'd a Criminal of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I will have no more reſpect nor regard, but leſs, for him, than I wou'd for any common Offender. And therefore, without the hopes of Reward, or the fears of Puniſhment, I cleclare in the preſence of the Almighty, if I knew any part of the <hi>Papiſh-Plot,</hi> or the Perſons concern'd in't, I wou'd long ſince have reveal'd the whole Contrivance: But none in their ſenſes can believe, that a known <hi>Proteſtant</hi> cou'd be made pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to ſuch a Conſpiracy; to which, if neceſſary, might be added, that I was in a Country remote from that, where the Deſign is ſaid to be hatch'd.</p>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:29655:8"/>
                        <p>I own my ſelf of ſo extenſive a Charity, as to love the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all honeſt Men, notwithſtanding their differing from me in opinion, about the Modes and Circumſtances of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to be for Liberty of Conſcience, when conſiſtent with the ſafety of the ſtate, to all quiet and peaceable Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; But when 'tis urg'd and made uſe of to other ends, or as a Cloak for Rebellion or Treachery, I abominate all ſuch Indulgence.</p>
                        <p>But I will no longer dwell on this Subject, than to mind you of Collonel <hi>Manſel</hi>'s miſtake or forgetfulneſs, when he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms this Honourable Houſe, <hi>That in or about July</hi> 1678. <hi>I din'd at his Treat for a</hi> German <hi>Lord, in or der to a Deſign of his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Forreign Command, and that</hi> 2 <hi>or</hi> 3 <hi>days after, Iſhou'd adviſe him againſt it, telling him the Duke wou'd very ſoon have occaſion for ſuch Officers.</hi> Firſt, I do ſay, to have ſaid ſo was no Crime; But I eaſily ſee through this Artifice, 'tis to ſerve as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I underſtood ſomewhat of the Plot, of which I am as ignorant as any man living, beyond what I have ſince learnt from the Prints and publick Fame. In the next place, I do ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny I ever ſaid the words, becauſe I do not know the Duke had any ſuch Deſign, and am certain I connot invent. Beſides, by many circumſtances, needleſs here to mention, that Dinner was after the Courts return from <hi>Windſor,</hi> and conſequently after the breaking forth of the Plot. I deſire the Gentleman wou'd recollect himſelf; at that time he was very great and intimate with a Roman Catholick, <hi>H. N.</hi> from whom if he heard not the words, as I am not apt to imagine, I am confident he dream'd them. He cannot be ignorant that I knew why he was disbanded in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. and that I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways declin'd, not only as having no Intereſt, but as unwilling for other reaſons, to introduce him to the Duke, as he often preſs'd; and therefore he made his application to others, but with as ill ſucceſs.</p>
                        <p>And now give me leave, I beſeech you, Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> to anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer an Objection, that I ſhou'd have preſcrib'd a way how the King ſhou'd live without Parliaments: I am ſo far from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29655:9"/>entertaining ſuch a thought, that I ever eſteem'd the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>England</hi> by King, Lords and Commons, the happieſt kind of Government in the world; and if the diſcourſe called, <hi>The Riſe and Tower of Parliaments,</hi> &amp;c. be mine, of which many will have me the Author, the reading it, wou'd be of this a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Confutation: In that, Parliaments are magnifi'd, their power rather enlarg'd than leſſen'd, and their frequent meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings recommended as moſt convenient.</p>
                        <p>In a word, whatever Character my Adverſaries have given of me, I am not a <hi>Proteſtant in Maſquerade,</hi> I can neither Lie nor Diſſemble, I am really what I profeſs, and as the word is commonly taken, no lover of <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Government, in any ſingle or complicated Body.</p>
                        <p>As to the Letter ſubſcrib'd by <hi>Fitz James,</hi> I do ſincerely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt I have no Acquaintance with any of the Name, nor ever ſaw the Hand before, nor the intended Meſſenger <hi>C.</hi> who not finding me, left it with the Maid-Servant: But in this there is nothing Criminal,</p>
                        <p>As to the Computations, they are a Tranſcript from a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Sir <hi>Peter Petts,</hi> containing the number of Conformiſts, Non-conformiſts, and Papiſts, throughout <hi>England,</hi> taken by the Biſhops order, in or about the time of the <hi>General Indal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> and by him produc'd preſently after the <hi>Plot,</hi> upon the talk that there were fifty thouſand Papiſts, able to bear Arms, within <hi>Temple-Bar</hi> and about <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> a number near double to what, at the taking this ſurvey, they were found, Men, Women and Children, in the whole Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>For the Copy of my Couſin <hi>Wilſons</hi> writing, I confeſs it the only thing I endeavour'd to evade, having ingenuouſly, and without reſerve anſwer'd all other queſtions. That individual Paper I never ſaw before the preceding night, when meeting it in the Drawer of my Bed-Chamber, (always open, whether I am at home or abroad) I laid it uppermoſt with purpoſe of inquiring how he came by it, and whether he knew the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; but not ſeeing him till next day in preſence of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſent to ſearch my Lodgings, I cou'd not ask him, and was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29655:9"/>ſurpriz'd to have ſo Indiſcreet and Reflective a Paper found in his hand, and among mine. 'Tis true, that about three weeks before, I found another of the ſame Contents, in an old crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed hand, to me unknown; which after I had read, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded it might poſſibly be left by ſome of my Acquaintance in their Viſits, and being unable to gueſs at the perſon, not knowing how long it had layn there, being dated above a Month before, I immediately threw it into the Fire. Yet in this Paper, which has made ſo great a noiſe, there is neither Felony nor Treaſon; and being the Act of another, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by me publiſh'd, having neither Sub, nor Super, Scripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor Writ to, nor from me, nor Copy'd by my order, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, I preſume, be a Libel, nor I hope imputed to me, to whom it came perfectly by Accident: If it were lawfull to ſpeak ones gueſſes from the Contents, it ſhou'd ſeem to have come from a Learned Gentleman, one of your own Members, then in the Country, skill'd in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue, to which both my Couſin and I are perfect ſtrangers; nor was either of us out of <hi>London</hi> then, or for ſome time before. If I cou'd as well hit upon the Perſon, as his Quality, I wou'd give a more ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry account of this matter; and I hope this Honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly will the ſooner credit me, when they reflect, that upon ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another Paper of my Kinſmans writing, I wou'd not by a Lie deny this to be his hand.</p>
                        <p>As for my writing to Mr. <hi>Gadbury,</hi> I refer my ſelf to the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Sir <hi>William Waller</hi>'s hands: I have told you the acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal occaſion; I deſir'd from him, (whoſe Acquaintance I knew large, even among the Members of that Parliament) the moſt material of publick News; I neither ask'd for Schemes or Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, I have ever laugh'd at the idle and ridiculous Art of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Aſtrology, invented, at leaſt practis'd, to impoſe upon, and pick the Pockets of the Ignorant and the Credulous.</p>
                        <p>And now as to the Cauſe of my Commitment: The ſtory Dr. <hi>D.</hi> told me as News, of <hi>Peter Norris</hi> his knowing as much of the Plot as any man in <hi>England,</hi> his going, or being gone into <hi>France</hi> to fetch a Prieſt to be a Witneſs, I can only ſay, as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29655:10"/>near as I remember, I gave the ſame account to Mr. <hi>Secretary;</hi> not as an Informer, but as News; for not being look'd upon as ſuch, I was not deſir'd to Swear, nor cou'd I to a hear-ſay. In this I call Heaven to witneſs I had no Siniſter deſign, but an Honeſt intention of having the full Truth brought to Light: Nor do I know, nor have I any reaſon to believe, that Mr. <hi>Secretary</hi>'s after proceedings were from any other princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Upon my telling him the Name of <hi>Norris,</hi> and his ſaying he had never before heard it, and commanding me to ſend the Doctor to him, or the others Deſcription; As ſoon as I met with the Doctor, which was ſeveral days after this Diſcourſe; and he as not knowing Mr. <hi>Secretary,</hi> reſuſing to go, I deſir'd from him the Deſcription, which ſometime after he brought me, I gave or ſent to Mr. <hi>Secretary,</hi> for I cannot tell whether. But of this I am certain, that all I knew of the Affair, was from the Doctor only; and that I never communicated it to any, but Mr. <hi>Secretary,</hi> and that by what I writ under the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, appears to be near a Month after <hi>Norris</hi> his departure, and conſequently cou'd not be deſign'd to ſtop his Journey, or prevent the Prieſts coming over, or obſtruct the fuller diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Plot, which no man living deſires more than my ſelf, believing it the Intereſt of every honeſt Subject and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, (out of which number I cannot be excluded) to have all in't, from the higheſt to the loweſt puniſh'd according to merit; and that tranquility it has ſo long diſturb'd, re-ſettl'd in the Kingdom: And now I hope none of the Members of this Honourable Houſe can imagine I cou'd be guilty of ſo Horrid a Crime, as having any knowledge of the Prieſts being poiſon'd, as is ſuſpected, or given out he might be. I am ſo ignorant of this, or any part of the Conſpiracy, that I do not ſo much deſpiſe, as decline, becauſe not needing it, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous offer of Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> or other Members Interceſſion for my Pardon: Lacknowledge, as I ought the Favour with all fitting reſpect; but I thank God, I am ſo Innocent, that I dare, as now I do, challenge the whole World, to make out one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisular, where in Word or Action, in the whole courſe of my
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29655:10"/>life, I have done or ſpoken falſly, or unjuſtly; and yet no man ever ſuffer'd more Calumnies without any cauſe, or the leaſt ſhadow of Truth, beyond the witty malice of thoſe, whoſe Eyes are blinded, and Conſciences ſear'd by Envy and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, who from pretended Friends are become my real Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, contrary to Reaſon and Juſtice. But ſurther, none can believe I cou'd keep any dangerous Correſpondence, when its well known that for theſe three years and a half all my Letters were no otherwiſe Directed, than for me at the <hi>Reyal Coffee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Beſides it appear'd at the Committee by <hi>Norris</hi> his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that this Prieſt <hi>Dowdall,</hi> (whoſe Name I never heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,) died <hi>september</hi> laft was twelve month, eight months be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I heard there was ſuch a man in the World as <hi>Norris,</hi> and at a time when I was in another Country. And ſince you have thought fit to acquit Dr. <hi>D.</hi> who was my Author and Principal, and who own'd himſelf a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> I hope you will not think it equal, that I a known ſincere Proteſtant, and but an Acceſſary, ſhould ſtand Committed, and Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after ſuch a manner, as neither Felon nor Traytor, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Accus'd, but Convicted, cou'd ſuffer a cloſer Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                        <p>And here, Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> I intreat your leave to ask Pardon, if at the Committee my Behaviour has offended any of the Members of this Honourable Houſe, and to ſay, whatever heat I expreſs'd, was the effect of Paſſion, to which I was mov'd, by hearing ſeveral of them in publick, as at <hi>Locketts,</hi> and other Eating and <hi>Coffe-Houſes,</hi> had call'd me <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and a ſecond <hi>Coleman,</hi> with other Aſperſions I cou'd not bear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reſentment: To this was added my being commanded a Meſſenger for Dr. <hi>D.</hi> (an Office beneath me,) and wherein I could not expect to be ſucoesful, not knowing whether he wou'd appear without Compulſion. I hope it will not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted an unexpiable Crime for a Gentleman of more Years and Diſcretion, than I can pretend to, to ſhew himſelf di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd at a conceiv'd Indignity or Affront; and in hopes it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29655:11"/>may not be accounted ſo hainous, I do once more with all due Submiſſion beg Pardon. There is one thing more I cannot without trouble touch upon, the Reflections the Written Votes, very different from the Printed, bring upon my Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. In thoſe 'tis ſaid, it appears that I have ſucceeded Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> than which there never was a more groundleſs, falſe, or malicious invention: And alſo that I queſtion'd your Authority, and ſaid your Proceedings look'd like the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. However Sir <hi>William Roberts</hi> came to make the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, my words were to Sir <hi>John Morton</hi> in another Room, and to him I appeal, whether they were not thus. Upon his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing that I ſhou'd fare the better, if I freely ſhew'd my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, I told him I wou'd not hide one, nor diſpute their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, though I had heard others did; and that the Seizing Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets and Writings, was not only Illegal, but look'd upon as one of the Cauſes of the laſt Rebellion; thereupon he wiſh'd I had not ſaid the Words: I reply'd, I ment no harm by thoſe Objections, and notwithſtanding my mentioning them, they ſhou'd find in me a readineſs to obey, and an intire ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and added, if they were offenſive, I unſaid them, and ask'd his Pardon, as I now humbly do from the whole Houſe, if I am thought herein to have offended: And to do Sir <hi>John</hi> Juſtice, he was pleas'd to promiſe he wou'd take no notice of the Diſcourſe, unleſs commanded; to whom with the reſt of the Committee I refer myſelf, whether of my own accord I was not going along with them, when I met your Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger.</p>
                        <p>If I had been guilty of any Crime, I had not only Warning, but Threats and Advices to fly many days, ſome Weeks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when I was told by Letters from unknown hands, and by ſeveral perſons of Honour and Quality, that I was deſign'd to be brought into trouble; I need not in this place ſay, for what reaſon. And here I cannot by the way but take notice of a Report made by Juſtice <hi>Warc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>p</hi> at this Bar, and ſpread at <hi>Coffe-Houſes;</hi> that he ſhou'd have Search'd Mr. <hi>Sheridans</hi> Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and there found only a parcel of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Books, whereas
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29655:11"/>he never was in mine, but at Mr. <hi>Brunetly</hi>'s Houſe, an <hi>Italian</hi> Merchant, whoſe Books choſe muſt have been; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope this was ſome Clarks, rather than his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake.</p>
                        <p>And now Once no Man can be plac'd beyond the reach of Malice, and the Devices of the Wicked, and that I happen to be brought hither as a ſuppos'd Criminal, I am extreamly pleas'd I have the good fortune to meet with ſo wiſe and equil Judges, as compoſe this Auguſt and Honourable Aſſembly; where I am ſo far from ſears, that I do not doubt, but upon an exact Scrutiny, and an Impartial Examination, my ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſo infinitely, and ſo wrongfully expos'd to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, will be ſo far from gratifying my Adverſaries unjuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, that they will not only be deſeated, but my ſelf greatly advantag'd; and therefore I leave my Cauſe at the Footſtool of your Juſtice, and willingly ſubmit to your Pleaſure and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations, praying no other favour, than what I am ſure you wou'd grant without asking; your full Conſideration of the whole Matter, your ſpeedy Condemnation or Acquittal, as I ſhall be found Guilty or Innocent.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The next Day after his Speech, Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi> was freed from his Cloſe Reſtraint, and his Confinement made more Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by the Liberty of Converſing with whom he pleas'd: A Committee was appointed to examine, whether the Paper found looſe in his Chamber, were of his <hi>Own,</hi> or <hi>Nephew</hi>'s Writing; though ſor it, as a Breach of Priviledge, the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi> had been Committed <hi>Five</hi> Days before. Where, by the way, it may ſeem odd, That Copying a Letter without Divulging it, becauſe therein a Member of the <hi>Houſe</hi> was reflected on, ſhou'd be a Crime deſerving ſo ſevere a Treatment, as the Commitment of a Young Gentleman of the <hi>Temple;</hi> who, Though he own'd it his Hand, and declar'd he Tranſcrib'd it for his own Uſe, as a thing Pleaſing and Witty in the Stile and Compoſition, was yet notwithſtanding, commanded (in their Preſence) to Write <hi>Three</hi> or <hi>Four</hi> Lines; which he did
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29655:12"/>with that Speed, that they cou'd not but be ſatisfy'd he did not Counterfeit. Some Malicious Perſons will have it, that his Crime was, his Relation to Mr. <hi>Sheridan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this <hi>Committee,</hi> both the <hi>Uncle,</hi> and the <hi>Nephew</hi> were treated, firſt Civilly, and after Roughly enough; the One threatned with the <hi>Pillory &amp;c.</hi> the Other with an intended Report to the <hi>Houſe,</hi> of his being a very dangerous Perſon. To which he reply'd, <hi>That he was ſorry ſuch an Opinion was taken up, without any Ground; that he cou'd not prevent their Pleaſure;</hi> only deſir'd, <hi>
                  <hi>They would do. as they would be done unto;</hi> and conſider, that he was as true a Proteſtant, as any in the Church of</hi> England; <hi>and as Honeſt a Man, as any in the Kingdom;</hi> that he <hi>Defy'd the diſproving of either of thoſe Two Truths; and if ſuch Men were Dangerous, none were otherwiſe, but Fools and Knaves.</hi> But what-ever was the Cauſe, 'tis obſervable, that this Report was never made, tho' the <hi>Committee</hi> Sate <hi>Thurſday</hi> the <hi>Sixteenth</hi> of <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, he was often told by ſeveral Perſons, <hi>That they heard, his Name wou'd be inſerted amongſt the Papiſts, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd Bill of Baniſhment:</hi> An Artifice too weak to ſrighten one of leſs Courage, who cou'd not but be aſſur'd, ſo unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable a Clauſe was unlikely to paſs the whole <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons;</hi> or, if it ſhou'd, it wou'd not the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords;</hi> the Great Conſervers of Juſtice, and the Supreme Tribunal of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſtood Committed <hi>Eifteen</hi> Dayes, at great and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Charges, and after all Inquiries and Searches, nothing Criminal being found againſt him; he was by ſome Friends, as well <hi>Members</hi> as others, together with his Coſin, that they might not ſeem Stubborn, prevail'd upon to Petition for their Releaſement; but to no purpoſe, ſome angry <hi>Members</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Reading of their Petitions. I am conſident, this cou'd not be the Senſe, becauſe not agreeable to the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> tho' per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to the <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Rules,</hi> of the whole <hi>Houſe;</hi> yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they were laid aſide.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sheridan,</hi> having now too much Cauſe to conclude, he was not like to be Releas'd during that <hi>Seſſion,</hi> ſince it was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29655:12"/>not in his Power to anſwer the Expectations or Deſires of ſome Perſons, reſolv'd to ſeek his Remedy by a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> upon a Statute lately made, to prevent Illegal and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Impriſonments; from which, if he cou'd not be freed, he hop'd from the <hi>Twelve</hi> Judges, and the <hi>Chancellor,</hi> if refus'd, to recover <hi>Six Thouſand Five Hundred Pounds</hi> Penalty, to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and Eaſe his Expence. But the Dread of the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> wou'd not ſuffer <hi>any</hi> of the <hi>many</hi> Counſellors or Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors he conſulted, to intermeddle in the Matter. Nevertheleſs, he was not diſcourag'd, but of himſelf purſu'd it, tho' with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Precedent, and contrary to the Advice of moſt of his Friends. I am loath to tell you, how very Nicely, ſome ſay <hi>Fearfully;</hi> the <hi>Judges</hi> proceeded in this Affair; moſt deſiring further time, and after avoiding being ſpoken with, unwilling to Deny, and not daring to Grant. But I were Unjuſt, if I did not let you know, that ſome wanted not courage; as my <hi>Lord Chancellor,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Jones,</hi> Sir <hi>Job Charleton;</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Weſton,</hi> who as oblig'd by Law and Conſcience, his Oath, and a late Statute, to his immortal Honour, at the firſt word gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Writ, made further Application to the others, unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Sir <hi>William Dolben,</hi> and Baron <hi>Gregory,</hi> were out of Town, or unconſulted. Of the reſt I will ſay no more at preſent; only tell you, Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi> is advis'd to bring his Action againſt ſeveral, particularly againſt Sir <hi>Francis North,</hi> and Judge <hi>Raymond:</hi> The <hi>last</hi> of theſe <hi>two</hi> thinking fit to ask the <hi>Commons</hi> advice, in this particular inſtance of doing that juſtice to a Subject, which all Judges are ſworn neither to <hi>Deny</hi> nor <hi>Delay.</hi> An Act of an extraordinary Nature, and without Precedent, for a Judge to expect Directions in the Execution of his Truſt, from the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> who are no Court of <hi>Judicature;</hi> and who, if the Caſe had been dubious, as here himſelf confeſs'd it was not, ought rather to apply himſelf to the reſt of the Judges, to His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy-Council, or to the Houſe of Lords; the laſt Reſort of Appeals in the Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29655:13"/>
            <p>I will paſs by this Judge's Servants denying his being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſending (as I am inform'd) for Sir <hi>Thomas Stringar,</hi> a Juſtice of the Peace, to examine the Gentleman that Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi>'s Buſineſs, and the Witneſſes, whether they were <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and wou'd take the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> &amp;c. which they, being Members of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> offer'd to do, to his great diſappointment.</p>
            <p>At length, after <hi>Twelve</hi> Days ſtrugling with Difficulties, not only with the Judges, but with inferior Officers; the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant at Arms</hi> was ſerv'd with the <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with acquaints the Houſe: They, after <hi>three days</hi> Debate, and <hi>thrice</hi> reading over the Statute, finding all ſo plain, cou'd not but leave the <hi>Serjeant</hi> in Obedience to the Writ, to carry his Priſoner before the Judge; who appearing with Mr. <hi>Sheridan,</hi> the Baron took the Names of <hi>three</hi> ſubſtantial Perſons, by him produc'd for Bail; declaring he wou'd ſend to the <hi>Speaker</hi> and <hi>Attorney-General,</hi> and if on <hi>Monday</hi> following (the utmoſt time allow'd by the Act) nothing more appear'd againſt the Priſoner, he ſhou'd then between three and four a Clock re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the benefit of his <hi>Habeas Corpus.</hi> But the <hi>Prorogation</hi> in the Morning prevented the Execution of the Baron's inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſet Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi> and his Kinſman <hi>Wilſon</hi> at liberty, after almoſt <hi>five</hi> Weeks expenſive Confinement; who, in all probability, had lain in Cuſtody during that Seſſion, how long ſoever, if a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> had not been then procur'd: Upon which, after Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi> had been diſcharg'd, his Kinſman expected likewiſe his Releaſement; there being no hopes his Petition wou'd be read ſince ſo often oppos'd by Mr. C. tho Mr. <hi>Godolphin,</hi> upon whoſe account he is ſaid to have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſent word he was ſorry he ſhou'd on his ſcore be ſo great a Sufferer; and promis'd, upon any others Motion, to ſee and that for his Liberty: Of which, many of that Houſe thought he had done nothing worthy the Forfeiture.</p>
            <p>And becauſe you have heard by the written Votes, that it did not appear to Baron <hi>Weſton,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi> was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> when he granted the Writ, you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29655:13"/>have here ſub-joyn'd a true Copy of his <hi>Petition,</hi> and <hi>Warrant</hi> thereunto annex'd, and deliver'd to the Baron.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To Sir <hi>Richard Weſton,</hi> Knight, One of the Barons of His Majeſties Court of <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head type="sub">The Humble Petition or Requeſt of <hi>Thomas Sheridan,</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Shewrth,</opener>
                        <p>THat Your Petitioner was on the <hi>Ninth</hi> of <hi>December</hi> laſt, Committed by one and the ſame Warrant, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Account, with Dr. <hi>D.</hi> (who was Releas'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Two Days after) into the Cuſtody of the <hi>Serjeant at Arms,</hi> attending the <hi>Houſe of Commons.</hi> That Your Petitioner humbly conceives he ought to be Bail'd, neither Felony, nor Treaſon, nor any other Crime, nor Breach of Priviledge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid to his Charge; as by the Copy of the Warrant of his Commitment here-unto annexed, does appear.</p>
                        <closer>He therefore Humbly prays, to have His Majeſties Writ of <hi>Habeas Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> according to the Statute made <hi>Triceſfimo Primo</hi> of the now KING.
<signed>And Your Petitioner ſhall Pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="warrant">
                        <head>The Copy of the WARRANT.</head>
                        <p>By Vertue of an Order of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> Aſſembled in Parliament, this Day made, Thrſe are to Will and Require you to keep in ſafe Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Bodies of Mr. <hi>Sheridan,</hi> and Mr. D. ſeparately and apart, <hi>DURING THE PLEASURE OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS.</hi> And you are not to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer or admit any Perſon to them, other than ſuch as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29655:14"/>ſhall have Occaſion to bring them Neceſſaries: And for your ſo doing, this ſhall be your Warrant. Hereof fail you not, as you will anſwer the Contrary at your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under my Hand <date>the <hi>Ninth</hi> Day of <hi>December,</hi> 1680.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>William Williams,</hi> Speaker.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <trailer>To <hi>John Topham,</hi> Eſquire, Serjeant at Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </trailer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>It is very obvious, and natural to obſerve from recounting to you this Caſe, that the <hi>Great Charter of England,</hi> or <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> was little thought of, or that I am much miſtaken in its meaning; ſince nothing is more expreſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, than that any Man ſhou'd be Impriſon'd, or Diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iz'd of any part of his Free-held, Goods, or Chattels (among which, are to be reckon'd all things a Man is Law fully poſſeſt of whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letters, Papers, or other Matters) without due proceſs of Law. <hi>Py</hi> 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. it was Enacted, <hi>That none ſhall be taken by Petition or Suggeſtion made to the</hi> King, <hi>or to his</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Parliament is</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>King's</hi> Great Council.</note> 
               <hi>Council, unleſs it be by Indictment, or Preſentment of good and lawful People of the ſame Neighbourhood, where ſuch Deeds be done in due manner, or by Proceſs made by Writ Original at the Common: Law; and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne be put out of his Franchiſe, or Free-hold, unleſs he be duly brought in to anſwer, and fore-judged of the ſame, by the Courſe of the Law.</hi> And 28 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. it is Ordain'd, <hi>That no Man, of what Eſtate, or Condition ſoever he be, ſhall be put out of his Lands and Tenements, nor taken, nor impriſoned, nor diſ-inherited, without being brought in to Anſwer by due Proceſs of Law.</hi> 42. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.6.3. 'tis Decreed; <hi>That no Man be put to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer without Preſentment before Juſtices, or Matter of Record or by due Proceſs, and Writ Original, according to the Old Law of the Land: And if any thing be done to the contrary, it ſhall be void in Law, and holden for error.</hi> Likewiſe, in the Petition of Right, 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 'tis Complain'd of by the <hi>Commons,</hi> as a great Grievance of the Subject, <hi>That againſt the Tenor of the ſaid Statutes, and other the good Laws, and Statutes of this Realm to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29655:14"/>that end Provided, divers of</hi> His Majeſties <hi>Subjects have been Impriſoned <hi>Without any Cauſe ſhewed;</hi>
               </hi> and when for their Deliverance, they were brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Juſtices, by <hi>His Majeſties</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Which by the by, were not then Denied, though the Laws were not half ſo full and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, as the late Statute.</note> Writs of <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> there to undergo and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, as the Court ſhould Order; and their Keepers Commanded to Certify the <hi>Cauſe of their Detainer;</hi> no Cauſe was Certified, but that they were Detained by <hi>His Majeſties <hi>Special Command.</hi>
               </hi> And 37 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 18. 'tis Enacted, <hi>That though it be Ordained in the</hi> Great Charter, <hi>that no Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Taken, nor Impriſoned, nor put out of his Free hold, without Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the Law; nevertheleſs, divers People make falſe Suggeſtions to the</hi> King <hi>himſelf, as well for Malice, as otherwiſe, where the</hi> King <hi>is often Grieved, and divers of the Realm put in Damage, againſt the Term of the ſame</hi> Charter: Wherefore it is Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>That all they who make ſuch Suggeſtions, ſhall be ſent with the ſame Suggeſtions before the</hi> Chancellor, Treaſurer, <hi>and his</hi> Grand Council; <hi>and that they find there Surety, to purſue their Suggeſtions, and incur the ſame Pain, that the others ſhould have had, if Attainted, in caſe that his Suggeſtion be found Evil.</hi> Or as it is alter'd in the following <hi>Parliament,</hi> 38 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>It is Aſſented, that if he that maketh the Complaint, cannot prove his intent againſt the Defendant, he ſhall be Commanded to Priſon, there to abide till he hath made gree to the Party of his Damages, and of the Slander that he hath Suffer'd by ſuch Occaſion; and after ſhall make Fine, and Ranſom to the</hi> King. In the Statute 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. 'tis Declared, That the Reaſons for putting down the <hi>Star-Chamber-Court,</hi> was not only founded on their Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to former Statutes; but that it was alſo an intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable Burden to the Subject, that the Remedies for all Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, might be had in the ordinary Courts of Juſtice; and that it was the means for introducing <hi>Arbitrary Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay then, if the ſame things are Exercis'd, and the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes remain any where elſe, they are equally to be Diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanc'd, and Explode'd by <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> and all Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29655:15"/>Subjects: And if the <hi>King</hi>'s Officers or Miniſters, from the Higheſt to the Loweſt, do any Illegal Act, though by the <hi>King</hi>'s expreſs Command, they themſelves become Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal: it cannot be ſuppos'd, that any Officer of any Court whatever, or Power inferior to His Majeſties, can have a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Latitude; but that whoever Executes any unlawful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to the Prejudice of his Fellow Subject, muſt be Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Party agriev'd, and lyable to make him Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; notwithſtanding any Illegal Warrant whatſoever.</p>
            <p>He that Conſiders the great Charge of <hi>One Pound, Six Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> and <hi>Eight Pence per Diem,</hi> Fees to the Serjeant, and his Meſſenger, beſides Diet, and Lodging at Pleaſure, will believe no Man ought to Suffer under that Puniſhment but upon good Grounds, and in conformity to former Laws, without the Accuſers giving Security for Proſecution and anſwering Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, if the Party prove himſelf Injur'd. 'Tis known Maxim in our Laws, that <hi>Carcer it ad cuſtodiendes, non ad pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niendes homines,</hi> before Tryal or Conviction; which was ſo far from being Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi>'s Caſe, that he was Committed, <hi>During Pleaſure</hi> to a Chargeable Confinement, without Cauſe Alledg'd, or any Information upon Oath; which is very Remarkable, if we conſider <hi>Noris</hi>'s Caſe, which was Voted by the ſame Houſe, that reſtrain'd Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi> in this manner, Illegal and Arbitrary, becauſe there was neither information upon Oath, nor Crime Specifi'd; and ſure, no Man can conclude the <hi>Commons</hi> may do that againſt a Subject, which the <hi>King</hi> cannot, without ſome Statute, giving the one that Power, which is Deny'd by all to the other. But, as the <hi>King</hi> can do no Wrong, though his Officers may; ſo I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to admit, if they Challenge the ſame Priviledge, that the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> may be always in the Right, provided they allow, that in the Execution of their Injunctions, ſome of their Members, and Miniſters, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t; though the whole Body may be exempt yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe do run the hazard of being call'd to an Account.</p>
            <p>I am certain, 'twas in order to Vindicate the Right of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29655:15"/>Subject, as well as to retrieve his own Liberty, and free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self from Charge, Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi> attempted the <hi>Habeas Corpus;</hi> a Motion, that no doubt offended ſome, though not the diſintereſſed part of the Nation, nothing tending more to the advantage of the People, and the oppoſition of Arbitrary Power, at leaſt equally to be contended againſt in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as in the King, by every free born Subject; who if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity makes him a Slave, and he have the Liberty to chuſe, ought and muſt preſer one Maſter to many. And tho it was three ſeveral days debated in the Houſe, and that ſome were of opinion, the Act was not deſign'd in favour of any by them Committed, the contrary was ſo plain from the Words, that it was never brought to a Vote. And I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd that one of the moſt Eminent and Deſervedly Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of the Houſe, a Manager of my Lord <hi>Staffords</hi> Tryal, Mr. <hi>P.</hi> advis'd their proceeding according to Law, in a Caſe where the Right of the Subject was ſo Nicely concern'd; and which was indeed, or might be, every <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man's, in which preſent and future Ages were equally intereſſed, and in which a Vote, not having at all the force of a Law, nor the expoſition of a Statute, might not only Reflect, but make them Odious to all the World: An advice, which all the People in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ought to acknowledge with Gratitude; nothing being more certainly the true Intereſt of the Nation than to keep all things within their proper Bounds and Channels; the King to continue to Both Houſes of Parliament, what the Lords have by Fundamental Conſtitutions alwaies enjoy'd, and the Commons by their conſtantly renew'd Petitions have receiv'd from the Kings Favour, their accuſtomed Right, and Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; and neither Lords nor Commons to Entrench upon, or offer violation to any of their Soveraigns Prerogatives, which (as the great <hi>Coke</hi> ſayes) are as much the Peoples Safety as the Kings Honour.</p>
            <p>And indeed it were highly prepoſterous that the King, who is the Fountain, Spring and Head of Law and Juſtice, ſhould be concluded by this act, and the Commons ſhould not, who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29655:16"/>are the Loweſt part in the Legiſlative Power and who have no manner of pretence to Judicature, nor (by Original Right) even their own Members as is conſonant to Reaſon being all equal, and as ſuch, having no more Power over one another, than <hi>Hartford-ſhire</hi> has over <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or <hi>Oxford</hi> over <hi>Cambridge,</hi> agreeable to that known Maxim in our own, and the Laws of all Nations, <hi>Paribus in pares non datur poteſtas.</hi> It plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the Puniſhments of breach of Priviledge againſt any of the Commons, was order'd upon their applications, by the King or Lords, and never any by themſelves inflicted before the latter end of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Reign, when the caſe of <hi>Ferrers,</hi> becauſe extraordinary, was referr'd to 'um by the Lords, as you will ſee in <hi>Crompt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi>'s Juriſdiction of Courts. And at this day 'tis certain, the Commons can force none into the cuſtody of their Serjeant, but in the caſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory Perſons are under a neceſſity of begging the Kings aſſiſtance, as is plain not only from Mr. <hi>Stowel</hi>'s refulal to go along with their Meſſenger; but likewiſe from their printed Votes of the <hi>8th</hi> of this inſtant <hi>January,</hi> concerning Sir <hi>John Lloyd,</hi> &amp;c. However, ſince conceſſion or continued uſage have given them Power over their own Members, or over others guilty of Breach of Priviledge, let them in Gods name enjoy it ſtill; but let them not Vote any thing they pleaſe a Breach of Priviledge, ſince they are known, and no other than what they ask at the beginning of every Parliament from the King's Grace, and are recorded, as firſt beg'd in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's days by Sir <hi>Thomus Moor,</hi> then Speaker. To act other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, is to ſet up an Arbitrary Power, never to be endur'd by any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, unleſs the moſt deſpicable of Cowards and Betrayers of his Country-Liberties. For, as the Commons are the Repreſentatives of the Nation, ſo they are choſen to defend, not invade their own, when out of that ſtation as well as the Peoples, Priviledges.</p>
            <p>While this Proceſs was on foot, Mr. <hi>Sheridan</hi> had many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes and Advices to Petition a ſecond time; which he not only refus'd before at the Serjeants inſtance, but after alſo at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29655:16"/>that of others; and that you may be fully ſatisfi'd of this Truth, read the following Letter on this occaſion to one of the Members, Sir <hi>R. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>HAving been inform'd, firſt by the <hi>Serjeant</hi> of Your <hi>Houſe,</hi> and after by my old Acquaintance Mr. <hi>Fermin,</hi> of your Favour towards me, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without Ingratitude but return you my hearty and humble Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſo great an Obligation: But having formerly petition'd with great deference and reſpect to the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> otherwiſe againſt my own judgment and reaſon; and that not being read, having no new matter to offer, I will not give you the trouble of a ſecond. I am apt to think, when any Cauſe is examin'd, it will be found amongſt the hardeſt. Dr. <hi>D.</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Papiſt, and Author of the Story, being diſcharged without Fees or Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in two days; and I a known Proteſtant kept Priſoner twenty five, tho both committed for one and the ſame Cauſe, or rather no Cauſe, none being mention'd in the Warrant; and for eight of thoſe days kept cloſer than a Felon, or a Traytor. Had my firſt been diſlik'd for matter of form, I might have preferr'd another, which now I think wou'd not be proper. Beſides my own ſufferings, my Coſen likewiſe taken into Cuſtody for Copying a Paper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining no Criminal, tho Reflective matter, as a Breach of Priviledge, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Member mention'd; and yet four days after, a Committee appointed to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, whether or no it was his Writing. I hope Sir, when theſe things, and the Reflections unjuſtly thrown upon me, are fully conſider'd, I ſhall have my liberty, for which I will own my ſelf oblig'd to you, and on all occaſions ſtudy to approve any ſelf, what I really am,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>SIR,</salute>
                           <signed> Your moſt humble, and very much oblig'd Servant, <hi>T. S.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>I have induſtriouſly avoided in this Narrative, the overtures I have heard were made Mr. <hi>S.</hi> becauſe not to be mention'd without Reflection on one ſide, or too much Honour on his. Tis enough, that he reſiſted all manner of Temptations, that cou'd betray or diſcover a Propenſion to diſhoneſty or cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize; and that as he had ſpoken and given it under his hand, ſo he wou'd make his Actions juſtifie his words, that he wou'd
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29655:17"/>by all poſſible means promote the good and ſervice of his King and Country, without making Shipwrack of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and that Reputation, which though clouded for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he neither cou'd nor wou'd forfeit.</p>
            <p>I will add no more, than to Engliſh what a wiſe <hi>French</hi> man, in ſuch an occaſion has Recorded: <hi>Si vous jegez ſurles apparences, vous ſeriz ſouvent trompet: Ce qui paeroiſt n'eſt preſque jamais la verite.</hi> If you wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not be deceiv'd, judge not according to Appearance, but judge Righteous judgment. He that has liv'd any time in the World, ought in paſſing his Cenſure upon others, to conſider whether he himſelf has never been traduc'd or heard groundleſs ſtories, if he have not, he has had extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary good fortune; if he have, he ought to be very ſlow in giving credit to Reports, which are ſometimes rais'd upon very little, and ofter without any, grounds.</p>
            <p>This has been notoriouſly Mr. S's. Caſe; no man was ever more loudly clamour'd againſt, nor more without cauſe, as appears, in that after al ſcrutinies he is found Innocent; inſomuch that one may well ſay. Here has been not onely a Great Cry, and a Little, but no Wool; abundance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Smoak without any Fire. Though his envious Adverſaries will have it that his Cunning only protected him, I do not doubt but you will believe the contrary knowing from many years intimate Acquaintance, no man is more free and open has leſs of craft or ſebtilty; and conſidering his ten pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none has more cauſe to ſtudy to preſerve from danger the ſimplicity o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Dove by the Wiſdome of the Serpent: A Caution, if ever uſeful, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this time more particulary neceſſarly.</p>
            <p>Through his Sides, 'tis well known, a very great Perſon was ſhot at who perhaps will be found Invulnerable. Dog<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Bark at the <hi>Moon</hi> in vain Some Spots there may be in that Great and Glorious Body, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as can render it uſeleſs or in ſignificant to any man of Sence or Reaſon</p>
            <p>Conclude then of all men by your own experience. and not upon the Relation of either Friends or Enemles; the firſt are not more Partial. then the laſt malicious. I ſhould play the Fool extreamly, if I give you Advice, who of all the World has the leaſt need of any; and therefore not having deſign'd this to you, without begging your Pardon, I will take the Liberty without further Apology, abruptly to Subſcribe my ſelf what I truly am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord</salute>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <signed>Your Grace's with all imaginable Reſpect and Sincerity, L. C.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> the 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, 1680/1.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29655:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
